<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nevves from the Lovv Countries</title>
            <title>Newes from the Low Countries.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B14966</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854748</idno>
  <idno type="VID">177433</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240938414</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 18507.26</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S119541</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.  Navigations series.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99854748e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B14966)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177433)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1133:7l)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nevves from the Lovv Countries</title>
                  <title>Newes from the Low Countries.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By M H,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Altmore [i.e. London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Iuly 29. 1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title. Actual place of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 18442.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 5747a on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Europe --  History --  1517-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="newsbook">
            <pb facs="tcp:177433:1"/>
            <head>NEWES FROM THE LOW COVNTRIES.</head>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From Venice the 20 of Iune 1621.</head>
               <p>HEre are <hi>3</hi> Ambassadors arriued being sent from <hi>Bethlem Gabor,</hi> but as yet haue not audience by the Signiorie, what was the contents of their commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion is yet vnknowne, but expect tobe informed therof by the next Letters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From Constantinople the 28 of Iune.</head>
               <p>The great and mightie Lord, with all his so great forces is vpon his march toward Poland, which whole Ringdome he is wholy bent to spoyle, &amp; fully resolued to make tributarie vnto the Turkish Empire: and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al meanes this Sommer to make way through the hart of the Kingdome, euen to the strong &amp; mightie Cittie Cracaw, further it is obserued that the Cossacks and Polanders, left and forsaken Podolia and are retired back vnto Poland.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From Vienna in Austira the 21 of Iune.</head>
               <p>The Emperour haueing beene at Mariensel, where he had beene at his deuotion with the Archduke Charles, is now returned; in his passage through Mewstadt, the youg Prince of Anhalt being prisoner: haueing desired audience, &amp; withall entreating for mercie at the hands of his Imperiall Maiestie, whereof he was vtterlie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, yet was he the very same night visited by the Arch duke Charles, and was by him possessed of much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
               <p>The English Gentelmen that was com to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, and had giuen his Imperiall maiestie to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, that the Lord Ambassador <hi>Digbie</hi> was vnder way: is by his maiestie sent back againe to the said Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassador, for to aduise him to take his way towards Prague, and there to tarrie for his Imperiall maiestie: for he ment to betake himselfe theitherwards vpon the <hi>5</hi> of Iuly: but yet it is supposed as farre as men can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that, that his iorney may be deferred to some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time, because of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Hungarian affayres where mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecs doe not fall out according to the desire of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour: especially considering y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> the Count of Bucquoy could not by no meanes preuent nor hinder y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> entrance of the <hi>4000</hi> men into Newhewsel which were sent thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for their succor and ayde: it is generally thought, &amp; that upon some good ground y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> if the besieged can hould out but for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> space of thrée weekes longer, which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt they can, for they want neither men, meat, munition, nor mony, but are sufficientlie prouided for of all necessahies, that Bucpuoy of necessitie shalbe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with all his leger to breake vp, and to returne back some other way, for <hi>Bethelem Gabor</hi> doth fortifie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe extraordinarilie strong with Turks, and Tarta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians being now wholy readie to march vp with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same for the reliefe of Newhewsell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From Vienna the 8 of Iuly.</head>
               <p>Whereat the count de Bucquoy who haueing to lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle purpose layen so long afore the Cittie Newhewsel in Hungaria, resoluing now to take a more serious view of the Cittie, to the end they might the better fit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues in bringing their cannons to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> most conuenient places for battering, made out of their campe by night in tending with the breake of day, in the twilight to effect their purposes, &amp; to that end as is Bucquoy: Maxemil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ian of Lightenser the Lord of Diepenbuch and others to the number of <hi>40</hi> speciall men of note went out, but whereas they went out <hi>40</hi> ther returned not the halfe as they went, for the Hungarians who slippe not away their advantage) liuing then in the woods next by, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passed them so about, that they went very neere to the taken or slaying of them all, and it was very narroulie that Bucquoy himselfe of escaped, but how soeuer it fell out that he esaped yet there remayned dead <hi>18</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the rest sorelie hurt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From Lipswick the 18 of Iulv.</head>
               <p>In Silesia vpon the Emperour his side it stands not well but very slightlie for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cruell and bloodie execution at Prague the <hi>21</hi> of Iune of thrée Earls and Lord: <hi>7</hi> knights the rest Councellors and Cittizens to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>47</hi> in all, hath bread such distast discord &amp; dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion euen vnto desperation of any hope of good mild or gentill dealings at the hands of the blood thyrstie Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, so that the said states of Silesia take on great store of men for their owne and counteries defence. In like manner the Marquisse of iegere Dorp lay there with his Souldiers who had strongly beset the Cittie Newes, &amp; the Earldome of Glets, besides that he was fallen into Bohemia wigh <hi>10000</hi> braue old Souldiers.</p>
               <p>In respect whereof the Corronel <hi>Sassen</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded that he should with his <hi>6</hi> cornets or companies of horsemen breake vp from Prague, and so march vp to Koningsgets, otherwise Kinggrets: likewise the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronell of wallenstegn was ready with certaines com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of foote to follow for the resistaunce of them of Iagerens dorp so much as possible they could.</p>
               <p>It is also signified that the young Graue of Thurin who holds him by the Marquisse of Iagerens Drop be-<hi>4000</hi> men strong, is fallen into the Dukedomes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>schen and Toppau, and therein taken the best passages and strongly beset the same. The Graue of Mansfield lies with his whole leger vppon the fronties of Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia most in the vpper Palatinate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Letter which Graue Mansfeld wrote to Bethelem Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor King of Hungaria whereby he shewed his Christian Resollution.</head>
               <p>Most Illustrious Prince mighty and puissant King most gratious Lord, and howsoeuer my gracious King and Lord, the great and bitter misfortune crossing his Maiestie in Bohemia, happening so much against him to the excessiue griefe and hart sore not of me alone, but also of all his true and faithfull subiects, yet on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, all true Christian Professors of the Gospel re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce no lesse to see and behold your Maiesties not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie great loue manifested, but also your most heroicall and magnanimous hart, wherewith you affect both the Kingdome of Bohemia, and all the confederate Lands: and not onely so, but therewith all your great zeale for the planttacion of the Gospell, euen the true Religion and speciall care for pretecting all sincere honest men from the tyrannie of the Pope, and the crueltie of the Spanish yoke.</p>
               <p>As for me I haue alwayes from the beginning vnto this present, to the vttermost of my power furthered, and wil not be backward in going on according to my dutie for the performance of my promise withall fidelitie, to his Kinglie Maiestie of Bohemia in the doing of al that shalbe profitable seruiceable, to my gratious King and Lord, as also to the whole Kingdome to my vtmost en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours: In consideration whereof I haue alwayes
<pb facs="tcp:177433:2"/>kept vnder obedience of his Maiesty Cittis the Tobor and Wittenkaw and against all onsets of the eneime, I haue constantlie and manfully defended and pretect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the same, I tooke Tackhaw by Gods permission out of the hands and power of his enimies, and haue now for the defence thereof beset it with men of warre: the Cloyster Doepel aright neast of murtherers, I haue disabled, Slecthen wald with there owne consent, I haue taken in euen as they of Ellenbogh did by Creits in which Cittie the inhabitants besides the Souldiers therein haue hitherto truelie, and faithfully, as became resolute souldiers, held and carried themselues, caused y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> enemie to retire, renewing their promises constantly and faithfully to mayntaine the Christian Religion: &amp; their beloued natiue Countite, &amp; therevpon to hasard both life &amp; goods, whicher also I haue with the first con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencie resolued to betake my selfe, Moreouer &amp; let all the bordering Citties Townes and Castels, which the enemie may set on, or besiege, be prouided for of all manner of prouision, I entend also by Gods grace, and that ere long to attempt some notable matter of waight and in portaunce, for &amp; meditate continually, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinke me night and day, how &amp; by what meanes this Tyrannicall Austria, and this heauy &amp; cruell Spanish yoke might be shaken off, and expulsed and this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome brought againe to its former estate, and so holpen to its desired peace. For which cause I could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale from your Kinglie Maiestie, how that Spayne hath other sufficient imployments, otherwayes, as also that the Duke of Sauoy my most gratious Lord, with the mightie Duke of Venice, wilbe imployed in some notable seruices, the Swithers haue held hard by the King of France for helpe, for the recouerie of veltolia the States of Hoolland wilbe armed both by sea &amp; Land it were vame to say more of the Austrian councel tiran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall persecution, or of the two well knowne Spanish Inquisitions, I am also very busie in the taken on of men, hoping within a few weeks to haue <hi>15</hi> thousand thoren men of warre in readines, but considering that for the better expedition of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> warrs, I haue great neede of <hi>2000</hi> horsmen, my earnest suite therefore to your Maiestie is that you wilbe pleased and that withall possible speed to furnish me with the aforesayd number of <hi>20<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0</hi> Hungarian horsemen, if it be possible, and I as soone as I shallbe so furnished, will spare neither la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor nor paines for the erformaunce of that seruice, that may serue for the furderaunce of the Christiun religion, and the welfare of the Kingdome of Bohemia, for my fidelite wherein your Maiestie shall in nothing doubt: but without the said number of horse I shall not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to performe that seruice I would, which therefore I will expect with the first opertunitie: hopeing withall that your Maieste is and willbe an vpholder as of the Christian Religion, so also of this our natiue Countrie manifesing your selfe to be are that wil, not to suffer your selfe to be deceiued by the bloody Papists, nor yet to be drawne by their deceitfull pretences, to a faise faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse and vniust peace, the rather considiring that their cruell and abominable tyronies deceitfullnesse and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries are euery where too too manifest, which many doe dailie féele and vndergoe, and heartily bewaile with sighs and teeres: herewith concluding I will pray vnto allmightie God for your Maiesties prosperous raigne, the ouerenmming of your enemies and so ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly beséeching that he will be your protector I shall with longing expect your certaine resolution and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Meane time resting your Kingly Maiesties al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies most dutifull obedient <hi>Earness<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> Graue of Mansfield, Marquis of Niewcastle, Lord of Thaldrung and cheife gouernor and Mashall of his Maiestie of Bohemia, his men of warre.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <p>The rest of the prisoners in Orague are pardonned &amp; are discharged and let goe: Duke Luke onelie expected: and the commissionners of the Emperours were vpon their departure into Morauia towards Brm, not vnlike as is generally thought, but that some there also may be brought to the fleshbank vnder the hands of the like Butchers.</p>
               <p>THe Duke of Bauaria hath called togeither y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Stats of the Land vpon the Ens, for to acknowledg him their Lords and gouernors, or otherwise in case they will not, then to pay him <hi>2800000</hi> florins, which he hath on the of the Emperour disbursted and layd out.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From Cullen the 19 of Iuly 1621.</head>
               <p>The next wéeke shall the new Spaniards vnder the commaund of the Mark-graue of Ansbach his brother, be mustered and then shal remayne in the Palatinate.</p>
               <p>In Berghlandt <hi>6</hi> companies of foote march higher towards Niewborghs quarters, about Papen Muts for to hinder them of the fort or Schonce, that they may not cut any more of the willowes for the fortifiing of their Sconce.</p>
               <p>The Horsemen of the enemies, which were hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore brought into Butphen prisoners, are proclaimed for prise and are set vppon a ransome, their horses armor and weapons were by the sound of a Trumpet sould, Wherevpon Graue Hendrick Vanden Bergh a Span<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ish generall, hath written that he meant, that sith they on their side had as yet shewed no manner of hostilitie, that he thought it should be also on their side: so that the prisoners vpon his promise of contenting them, as for their ransome might be sent againe: wherevpon the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soners were discharged &amp; afterward departed to Zut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen.</p>
               <p>Newes from Brussels certifie that the Earle of Bucquoy is slaine.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed at Altmore by M H, Iuly 29. 1621.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>